<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

    <title><![CDATA[Tag: Node.js | Sample & Hold]]></title>
    <link href="http://sample-hold.com/tag/node-dot-js/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
    <link href="http://sample-hold.com/"/>
    <updated>2014-10-02T10:43:14+02:00</updated>
    <id>http://sample-hold.com/</id>
    <author>
        <name><![CDATA[Fred Ghilini]]></name>
        
    </author>
    <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

    
    <entry>
        <title type="html"><![CDATA[Review: Full Stack Web Development With Backbone.js]]></title>
        <link href="http://sample-hold.com/2014/10/01/review-full-stack-web-development-with-backbone-dot-js/"/>
        <updated>2014-10-01T14:37:00+02:00</updated>
        <id>http://sample-hold.com/2014/10/01/review-full-stack-web-development-with-backbone-dot-js</id>
        <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="alignleft" src="/images/backbone_hardcover.png"> In my current employment, I&rsquo;m contributing to a Single-Page Application using Backbone.js, a very popular library used in many frontend projects. Many developers would argue that Backbone.js isn&rsquo;t the easiest way to start your application, since it requires to build up the proper stack of technologies and libraries to address each topic encountered during frontend development. Some would prefer choosing a more integrated framework like AngularJS or Ember. On the pros side, Backbone.js is agnostic with respect of your preferred libraries, and coupling it with the right recipes leads to a truly efficient solution that solves you initial concerns, whether it be optimizing your SPA for mobile devices, desktops, or tailoring your application for a specific server-side technology.</p>

<p>During my researches I was led to read &ldquo;Full Stack Web Development With Backbone.js&rdquo; and share some practices with the author, Patrick Mulder, which is a Munich-based freelance software consultant. For anyone who is looking for any recent publications on Backbone.js, I&rsquo;ll try to summarize the outcome of this reading. <!-- more --></p>

<p>With less than 200 pages, &ldquo;Full Stack Web Development With Backbone.js&rdquo; is dedicated to those impatient readers who are, exactly like I am, eager to learn new things but not really into reading technical books. In overall, I had pleasure reading this book which has IMHO a correct balance between text and code snippets. I really enjoyed reading a concrete use case from beginning to end, evaluating the author&rsquo;s choices for solving each problem, because this is not the usual experience that you get when crawling API documentations or Stack Overflow-like blogs. As I&rsquo;m already using Backbone for a while, I however skipped a lot of content to get to the more advanced topics, and I would have expected more pages about them (Thorax for instance).</p>

<p>&ldquo;Review: Full Stack Web Development With Backbone.js&rdquo; will undoubtedly put non-experienced developers on track with Backbone.js, making them building a simple application powered by a Node.js server that embraces all core concepts. For experienced developers, there are many tips and tricks to take away: it&rsquo;s up to you to judge if it&rsquo;s worth reading the book or instead learn those tricks from other sources. At last, the biggest downside of this small technical book is possibly its size! There was a compromise made on a concise content, but this may not suit to everyone: both beginners and experienced developers may get frustrated of not being given enough details about Backbone.js itself, or about extensions and advanced techniques.</p>
]]></content>
    </entry>
    
</feed>